Siva Kumar

https://www.linkedin.com/in/sivakumarbv

sivavenkata86@gmail.com

+1 (832) 844 6753

Professional Statement:

I have Master's Degree in Information Systems with over extensive experience as a UI/UX Developer within the Financial, Insurance and Oil-gas domain as an in-house employee as well as a specialist consultant.

Extensive experience working with multiple technologies including, Angular (JS/2/4/6), HTML, CSS, .Net, PHP and SQL. Very strong with Angular and have used successfully on multiple projects involving Front-End Development.

Excellent communication skills with experience working alongside Business Team understanding their requirements and implementing this in to the software.

Experience:

- Work with Product Managers and Business Analysts to understand and implement complex business functionality
- Participate in the Agile methodology, including meetings, iterative development, estimations and design sessions
- Stay current with the newest online technologies; research new technologies and make recommendations on implementations
- Collaborate with Architects and other Software Engineering resources in designing and implementing integrated, enterprise solutions
- Deliver project assignments on time, within budget and with high quality
- Design, implement and unit test Web Application code
- Developing and re-factoring existing products, providing product enhancements and resolving product defects to meet customer issues
- Used JIRA to be tracking the bugs
- Utilized CSS based design techniques to eliminate table-based layouts and CSS Sprites to improve performance and decrease page load speed
- Implemented custom validation controls for various forms through Angular Components validation controls
- Implemented User Interface and integrated with backend code, Node JS as server-side technology
- Worked on writing extensive unit tests using frameworks and test runners like Jasmine, Mocha Chai & Karma etc. Worked on CSS pre-processors like SASS and LESS

Portfolio: sivabv.github.io

LinkedIn: https://linkedin.com/in/sivakumarbv/
Angular app deployed to sivabv.github.io/myapp

Education:

Master's in **Information Systems** from Iowa State University.

Skill Set:

SPA Services Singleton	Html CSS	Cucumber PHP Python	Sprint Planning Agile Source Tree
Dependency Injection Angular - Typescript Routes Modules Component Services Pipe NGRX/ RXJS Angular-JS Scope RootScope MVC4 D3.js OAuth Template Form Reactive Forms Angular Material	JavaScript jQuery SCSS SVG Canvas Less Preprocessor Unit-Testing Jasmine Karma Protractor Test Driven Development Behavior Driven Development End to End testing	ADA Accessibility Aria Page Load Optimization CSS Sprites Font Awesome Google Analytics SEO W3C Standards Git Jira User Stories	Adobe Photoshop Adobe Illustrator Balsamiq Invision Zeplin Axure .Net MVC C# VB .NEt Razor Syntax Kendo Ui Telerik Controls

Experience:

Trinity Industries, Dallas Texas Sr UI/UX- Developer

August 2018- Present



Responsibilities:

- Working on redesign and migration of Fleet Maintenance Application to Modern User Interface using Angular and Web API (.Net).
- Creation of Wire-frame using Balsamiq and Invision while discussing with Focus and User Group.
- Participation in user requirement Discussion and Sprint Planning.
- Using Angular module for creation of SPA application for report and work queue tasks.
- Analyze feasibility by presenting proof-of-concepts (POCs)
- Experience developing rich UI web based user interfaces including experience writing Object-Oriented
- Creation of angular Components, Services, Routes and pipes.
- Programming using RXJS and ngrx/Store. (State management)
- Using Typescript as programming language to create OOP JavaScript code to implement complex functionalities and calculation to project data on Tables.
- Implementation of Reactive forms for user to input Data and save data Http verbs Put, post, get delete and options.

- Working on CSS3 and SCSS elements to create pixel perfect html pages and making sure all the pages are responsive on all the supported devices.
- Very good experience and knowledge of modern techniques like tree shaking, AOT & JIT and webpack.
- Using agile methodologies to measure project progress, participating in User Story creations, evaluation of story points, resolving roadblocks for smoother environment.
- Implementation of Unit test cases to deliver product with industrial standard.
- Participating in code review session and setting standard for writing code which is readable and having a scope for future enhancements.
- Creation of Unit Test cases using Jasmine Frame work.
- Conduct design and code review session
- Enforce code quality and performance
- Learning to implement modern standard newer techniques in JavaScript.
- Using GIT for Version Control Management in combination with SourceTree and Bitbucket.

Environment: TFS, .Net(core 2), Postman, Docker, BootStrap, Angular Material, NGRX, Redux methods, AWS, GAC, WebPack, Typescript, Angular 7, SCSS, CSS3, Html5, Aria & W3C Standards.

First Command -- Financial Services, Fort Worth Texas

Lead Sr UI/UX- Developer

August 2017- July 2018



Responsibilities:

- Good working experience in writing Angular2/4/5 JS/JQUERY AJAX based web applications to improve the response time and extensively
- Experience in building scalable MEAN stack applications using MongoDB, Express.js, AngularJS and NodeJS.
- Creative in Designing the UI which provides user-friendly experience for the users
- Good exposure and hands-on experience in application and execution of Agile based project management methodologies
- Worked extensively on AngularJS SPA domains.
- Extensively used Grunt and Gulp as an associate to Node JS to establish the connectivity between database and client.
- Experience in making Responsive Web Pages using Media Queries and Bootstrap, Material Design lite for styling mobile applications.
- Expertise creating user validation forms and sending data to server using RESTful services.
- Developed CSS LESS and SASS styles on all the pages of an application and positioning of objects.
- Used Gulp commands for building and deploying the project. Used Bower for successfully implementing the dependencies
- Strong database skills, Object Oriented Programming and development knowledge in LMS.
- Performed unit testing using Jasmine along with integration testing Chrome Inspector to fix bugs and worked closely with QA team
- Responsible for maintaining versions of source code using SVN and GIT, GIT-Enterprise, VSTS.
- Followed Agile Software Development Methodology in the progress of the project



- Good hands on skills, willingness to learn new tools and technologies, hardworking, have analytical and debugging skills, ready to take and accept challenges
- Created automated Unit test plans and Performed Unit testing modules according to the requirements and development standards
- Sencha Ext JS and other web technologies like HTML, CSS, JAVASCRIPT, JQUERY, JSON, XML, and
- Experience in object oriented JavaScript programming and Sencha Ext JS most recommended pattern
- Good experience in unit testing by using Karma and Protractor
- Ability to design application on AWS taking advantage of Disaster recovery.
- Experience with various IDE's such as Visual Studio Code, Web Strom, Sublime and Notepad++.

<u>Environment:</u> Jira, BitBucket, GIT, ASANA, Sourcetree, IE/Chrome/FireFox, Jenkins, HTML5, CSS3, SASS, Bootstrap, AJAX Sublime-text, VS-Code, JSFiddle, Plunker, JSON, Visual Studio, Dreamweaver CC, Webstorm.

Schlumberger – Oil & Gas, Houston Texas

Sr UI/UX-Designer – Angular Developer

January 2017- August 2017

Responsibilities:

- Schlumberger
- Create high-fidelity, responsive mock-ups and put together slide decks for client presentations
- Design new concepts using Axure under direction of the Creative Director
- Involved in requirement gathering, designing, development, UI reviews, and maintenance.
- Designed and developed the agent portal using framework Angular 2.0 along with HTML5, CSS3, and Typescript.
- The portal is made responsive using CSS3, preprocessors like SASS, Bootstrap, and media queries to support desktop and tablets.
- Written modular, secure, and well-tested front-end code in Typescript, HTML5 and CSS using the latest web.
- Extensively worked using AWS services along with wide and in depth understanding of each one of them.
- Created Typescript reusable components and services to consume REST API's using Component based architecture provided by angular 2.
- Implemented HTTP requests using RxJs Observable library to handle multiple values over time
- Used SVN for version control and JIRA for defect tracking.
- Many of the tasks has been framed with different user stories and have been working in bi-weekly sprint model covering up to 10 -12user stories per iteration and getting the acceptance criteria for sign off.
- Define technical requirements based upon business requirements.
- Involved in Agile process, monthly Sprints, and daily Scrums to discuss the development of the application.
- Excellent User Interface Visual design in Adobe Photoshop/Fireworks

<u>Environment:</u> WebPack, Jenkins, Linux, Angular-Material, HTML5, CSS3, SASS, Angular-2/Angular-4, TypeScript, Plunker, JSON, Visual Studio, Dreamweaver CC, Adobe Photoshop, Illustrator, Inivision.

Key Bank Limited, Houston Texas

UI/UX Designer

January 2015 to December 2016



Responsibilities:

- As a UI/UX engineer, I went through the UCD process to redesign the website and led the interaction design process. I also conducted multiple user research studies including surveys, interviews, and created personas and user stories to support the reorganization for Key.com
- Worked on Angular JS, Node JS, for heavy DOM manipulation.
- Worked extensively on Twitter Bootstrap, RESTful web-services, HTML 4/5, CSS 2/3, JSON, Media queries for responsiveness.
- Worked on Agile and Waterfall methodologies and actively participated in daily SCRUM meetings to produce quality deliverables within time with good understanding of business cycle.
- Developed various UI (User Interface) components using Angular JS (MVC), JSON and HTML.
- Contributed as key resource of the "Angular 2 Framework Team" in conversion of existing UI screens of the application to Angular 2 based UI.
- Implemented various Validation Controls for form validation and implemented custom validation controls using Object Oriented JavaScript.
- Actively involved in using Angular JS, Bootstrap and HTML5 to enable client side date to meets specific criteria by applying various validation variables.
- Used Object Oriented JavaScript to designed dynamic client-side to web forms and simulate process for web application.
- Used various Core Java concepts such as Exception Handling, Collection APIs to implement various features and enhancements.
- Used Angular Js to build the UI components, developed filters to display different dimension of data and font size modifiers.
- Created forms to collect and validate data from the user in HTML and JavaScript. Responsible for checking cross browser compatibility and hence worked on different browsers like safari, Internet explorer, Firefox and Google chrome.
- Extensively used JQUERY, JSON, AJAX and DOM scripting to create interactive web applications like message posting and auto complete form validations.
- Developed IFRAME element to fetch and display the external pages that contains Java-Script/CSS code that runs when fetched via Ajax, the page is from an outside domain. Fixed issue related to that.
- Involved in development of front-end components using Spring MVC, JSP, JavaScript, JAVA, and JSON.
- Worked closely with back-end developers to find ways to push the limits of existing Web technology in service of creating the best possible user experience.
- Developed Ajax Tabs Content script to display content pulled from external files inside a DIV and organized via CSS tabs.
- Developing XML classes for loading the data from XML files deployed at the server.
- Developed designs in securing the application using form-based authentication using HTML, JavaScript, JQuery and CSS.

Environment: HTML5 APIs, CSS3, Angular JS, EXT JS, JavaScript, JSON, iOS, Android, JQuery, Restful services, Design Patterns, Canvas, Web Services, Windows XP, Karma and Jasmine

Iowa State University

Front End Developer, PHP

August 2013 to December 2014

IOWA STATE UNIVERSITY

Responsibilities:

- Used Bootstrap to create responsive layout.
- Used AJAX, JSON to interact between user and server.
- Web app maintenance including updating the content and solving bugs report.
- Designed the Front-end screens using JSF, HTML and CSS3.
- Interpreted business requirement into technical requirement.
- Responsible for the implementation of Web Design based on CSS3, HTML5, and Bootstrap Front-End Framework.
- Strong communication, analytical, and interpersonal skills working within cross-functional teams.
- Involvement in all stages of Software development life cycle, including Analysis, development, Implementation, testing and support.
- Maintenance of company homepage by optimizing functions that used jQuery, using alternative Bootstrap layout and solving bugs reports.
- Good experience in JavaScript frameworks Angular.js, Node.js, Backbone.js, Require.js, Ext.js, knockout.js and JQuery especially AJAX driven web applications.
- Attended team meeting every week.
- Worked on consuming JSON object creation, parsing on both client side as well as server side. http://www.htc.hort.iastate.edu/

Environment: PHP, WordPress, CSS, JavaScript, jQuery, HTML, WAMP, JavaScript, jQuery, AJAX

Infosys Limited

C# - .Net Developer

July 2011 to July 2013

Responsibilities:

- Worked with designer who designed user interfaces and prototypes for a web-based internal system.
- Worked on front-end pages developed in a professional manner using HTML, CSS, JavaScript, and JQUERY.
- Developed and implemented user interfaces as per latest W3C standards.
- Developed client-side validation, code using JavaScript and JQUERY.
- Creating cross-browser compatible and standards-compliant CSS-based page layouts.
- Involved in fixing Front-End issues with the layouts.
- Actively used XML (documents and transformations) for creating templates with dynamic data from XML file.
- Performed JSON data parsing using Angular JS to render the information on user interface pages.
- Developed new cross-browser accessible interfaces using Bootstrap, JavaScript and Angular JS.
- Involved in requirement analysis, design, development and deployment.
- Worked extensively on developing web services using .Net Framework 3.5, Asp.Net, C# advanced features, JavaScript, Ajax and Html.
- Involved in Web Services including REST based services.



- Involved in writing stored procedures, triggers, user-defined functions (UDFs), user-defined types (UDTs), and queries.
- Worked on Visual Studio 2010, SQL Server 2008 R2, Microsoft SQL Express.

 Basic iQuery front-end frameworks for web, responsive and mobile based web applications and

• Used SVN for version control and JIRA for defect tracking. Environment: .NET Framework 3.5, MS Visual Studio 2010, WPF, C#, HTML, AJAX, XAML, Windows Server XP, SQL Server 2008 R2, ADO.NET, & Team Foundation Server.